- Hey folks, and welcome
to the Learn UI design lesson on sizing.
Now, sizing your UI elements
kind of sounds boring
but it's actually one of the
most common beginner mistakes
to size elements incorrectly
or at least awkwardly.
Turns out that most things in
your UI design sort of have
a natural size that they
desire to be at, so to speak.
And there's a lot of logic
for why you might size things
one way versus another.
We're gonna dive into all of that today,
we're gonna look at two examples,
one mobile, one desktop,
we're going to cover three heuristics
for sizing elements in your UI design.
But overall, I would say if
you only take away one thing
from this lesson, let it be this,
anytime you get the temptation
to just size something
that you're not really
sure how big it should be,
some button, say, oh,
it's an important button,
I'm gonna make it 80 pixels tall, stop.
Before you make it 80 pixels tall,
go and look at a bunch of well designed,
professionally designed apps
and see what they're doing.
And if no one else is doing
anything like what you wanna do,
you're probably not making
the right sizing decision.
This is sort of a corollary
to Jakob's Law of User Experience
which you might be familiar with if you're
into the UX side of things as well.
In any case, let's dive into our examples
and see what we learn.
All right, today, we're gonna be looking
at a mock up for givewell.org
which is a nonprofit
that I've done a little bit of work with.
And this whole example is based loosely
on some of my concepts
that I've sent them.
Givewell.org is actually a
really cool organization.
They rank some of the
top charities on earth
in terms of number of lives
saved per dollar donated
and basically figure out like,
what is the most effective way
that you can actually make the
world better with a donation.
On this particular page,
this is in their top charity section,
they're showing one of their top charities
of all time which is a charity
that distributes preventative
antimalarial medicine.
You can see I've mostly
already aligned stuff
pretty much correctly
by the book according
to the alignment lesson.
And yet, just because nothing
is really sized quite right,
the page sort of has this
awkward appearance to it.
So we're gonna swoop in,
make a bunch of changes,
fix everything up nicely.
I'll talk about the logic for
why I'm doing what I'm doing
and then we'll translate
this page into mobile as well
and talk about how things differ
when you're designing for smaller screens.
So first things first,
let's start at the top left.
We've got this giant
hamburger button right here.
And it might seem a little bit goofy
in the context of this page
but I guarantee you this is one
of the things that I've seen
in the thousands of homework
submissions that I've seen
through Learn UI Design
comes up again, and again.
Very large icons, and very large
hamburger buttons like this
are just kind of oddly common
for beginner designers to do.
So we're definitely gonna
shrink this a little bit.
And I would say the main logic behind
what size your icon should be is,
for the most part, it
should sort of appear
as an extension of the text.
So this text is written with a
"pen of a certain thickness",
and we kind of want the icon
to be not too far from that.
We go into our pixel preview mode here,
just pressing Ctrl+P to see this.
You can see that perhaps the
text is about one pixel thick,
maybe a little bit more
in different places.
And for icons, typically one
pixel seems kind of wispy.
So what I like to do is make
things about two pixels thick.
I think that is a fantastic default.
Also, for what it's worth,
most icons that appear in your UI,
you should be able to fit within a box
that's 24 pixels by 24 pixels.
So this being 40 pixels
wide is definitely too big.
If I make that 24, then
it just becomes clear
I need to bring these a
little bit closer together.
Let's go ahead and do that.
And maybe I could make it even smaller.
There we go.
Now it's 20 pixels wide, 12 pixels tall
and feels about right.
We're gonna go ahead and
resize this text later on
but one thing that you can do is
if the icon being two pixels thick
or the stroke weight being two
pixels thick feels too much
for the text, you can
actually reduce the opacity
of the icon a little bit.
So if I do, say 80%, that
might balance it out nicer
with text that is nearby.
Of course, right now, we
haven't styled that yet.
So we can come back to
that when we need to.
Now let's look, we have
this search our site
and research thing right here.
This is gonna turn to a search bar.
And so we will want a search icon.
Let's go ahead and just
make that one custom.
Press O for an oval, hold
Shift to get a constant size.
Now again, I'm gonna want this icon
to be about the same
size as the other one,
so not more than, say 20 pixels wide.
So what I need to do, this
is 15 by 15 right now,
I'm gonna press Shift+X
to create a stroke instead of a fill,
just switches those in Figma
and we'll give it a two pixel stroke.
And I would do inside except I actually,
I need to do center because
what I'm gonna do now
is press P, get into the pen tool,
and I'm gonna go and extend the handle
of the magnifying glass.
And if you have the stroke
inside, you can't see it.
So it needs to be on the center.
So the sizing is a little bit
off 'cause it goes over here
and it goes over here.
So when this says the width is 19 pixels,
it's actually really just over 20
but overall, this feels fine enough
and I would just use this.
I'm gonna press H just to make that
a little bit lighter
too but we can come back
to exactly how light this should be.
And technically, it
shouldn't start as black,
it should start as the color
of the text and still be 80%.
And so this backs up what I
consider the first heuristic
for sizing elements in
user interface design,
which is to default consistency
or consistency first.
A lot of the sizing of icons has to do
with the text around it.
We're not making icons
bigger than 20 or 24 pixels,
simply because text is so rarely gonna be
that much bigger too.
And just bear in mind
this is a little bit small
for right now, we'll come
back to it in a minute.
But the whole general
idea, and I hit this home
in the icons video later on in the course.
So say make your icons
and your text look like
they were drawn with the same pen.
It's just one more way
to add some consistency.
One common icon sizing
mistake that I'll see
is if someone wants to use an icon,
maybe a bit like an illustration.
So let's say someone goes here
and we'll add the thumbs up
from the Quantum icon set
for our top pick.
The issue is if I say, to scale this icon,
use the hotkey K here,
and I make it say twice as big, 40 by 40,
then all of a sudden,
all these stroke weights here have doubled
and now it's twice as thick
and it's just kind of awkward.
The text would need to be much bigger,
which even if it is bigger,
it's still just gonna look
a little bit funky next
to this really big, chunky thick icon.
So one thing I highly recommend is instead
of just making an icon bigger
than it otherwise would be,
try enclosing it in a little circle,
just encapsulating it in a circle.
Do something like that,
grab this theme blue,
move the element to the bottom
and change the icon's
color to white instead.
Option+H, Option+V will
bring it to the middle there.
Seems about centered.
And there we go.
That's typically gonna
be a much better way
to sort of make an icon
take up a bit more space.
Now I said it's critically important
to go and look at what some apps are doing
that are professionally designed.
So I've just picked out Airtable,
this Vercel landing page
and an IDEO blog post
just kind of randomly.
And we'll look at what
these three sites are doing.
Each of them is professionally designed.
They're all very well done.
But what are they doing in terms
of the sizing of various elements?
One thing you can see with Airtable
is they actually have
a filled in icon style
for most of their icons.
So they're actually quite small.
And in that sense, they
don't really feel consistent
with the text, it's not necessarily
drawn with the same pen,
but they went ahead and accented them
with a different color
and so they feel like
these cutesy little drawings
that do sort of fit in.
But just keep in mind how
small each of these things are.
Like This might be the biggest one
and I would say that
doesn't even look like
it's more than 20 pixels by 20.
All right, I guess it is, 25 or something.
Vercel's, this nice landing page,
not a ton of icons up here.
But if we scroll down a bit,
they are doing the icon encapsulated
in a little circle here.
And it just gives you a sense of
you could imagine this icon
is not gonna really hold
its own next to this
sub header right here.
So putting it in the circle is a nice way
to kind of beef up the importance
of that particular icon.
And then IDEO.
I actually don't love this design as much
because these icons are quite small.
But compared to this massive
title and everything else
on this page being generally oversized,
it just feels a little bit out of place.
I suppose when you scroll down,
there's a little bit
more consistency here.
This does feel like it's drawn
with the same pen as this
or this or even this text right here.
So that's good.
So now we're gonna shrink this logo,
which in my opinion is
just clearly too big.
It's definitely more common
of a beginner mistake
to make a logo too big than too small.
And of course, there's
definitely some clients
who wanna see a big logo no matter what.
So it can be an uphill battle trying
to get it down to a nice size.
I am going to say to fit this image here.
And typically logo sizes can totally vary.
For something that's
longer than it is tall,
I would say I wouldn't wanna
go over maybe 200 pixels
as a width.
Once you get that big, it's
just gonna start being perhaps,
a little bit bulky.
And another way to think
about the logo size,
especially if it's just a text logo
or primarily text is how does it compare
to the headers on the page.
Honestly, the page title
should probably be much bigger
than the logo itself.
So this is all right.
And we'll see what we come
and do with this here.
But if this is functionally equivalent
to about size 30 text, that
seems plenty big to me.
Now, I will say that one time
that you see this broken a little bit is
when you have a logo
that's really complicated like this seal
on the New England Journal
of Medicine website.
And in this particular case,
the whole site is so nicely designed,
it doesn't seem to
really make a difference,
but having a logo be too
detailed makes it very tempting
to make it too large and overall,
overly detailed logos are one
of the top three logo mistakes
that I warn against in my
blog post linked below.
So this seems about fine.
Now let's talk about the header too.
Overall it's also been
weirdly common looking
at beginner designs to see
headers that are far too tall.
Typically, I think of making headers,
probably starting around
60, 70, maybe 80 pixels,
depending on how spacious you
want the overall feel to be.
But I would say anywhere from 50 to 90
is sort of a good range.
And this is actually kind of a good excuse
to talk about sizing of elements
where there's a lot of
uncertainty in general.
If I'm sizing this header,
I very much wanna come at it
from a fill left, fill
right sort of strategy.
I wanna figure out what's
definitely too small
and what's definitely too
big and then kind of end up
in the middle of those ranges.
So if I have to put in this
hamburger button and this logo,
I'm not gonna adjust the
spacing totally right now,
as well as we're
ultimately gonna make this
into a search bar like a little control
and this will become a full on button.
It does seem if we're
at whatever, 30 pixels,
this is definitely too small.
There's no breathing room for our logo.
We're gonna end up
making that logo so tiny
if it's gonna have any
breathing room around it.
30 definitely feels too small.
Even 40 is like a little more manageable.
But then on the other hand,
we could just keep expanding
this until we say like,
what is absolutely too big?
And I can imagine having some headers,
especially if we work this in
where the total height is
100 pixels or 110, 120, fine,
but maybe at about this point,
I'm just thinking this is
actually getting way too big.
At this point, we're at 149.
So basically 150 pixels tall
and we're already eating
up a significant amount
of the screen real estate here.
Likewise, our logo, even
if we center it here,
just feels like it's lost in space,
it's absolutely just floating
in the middle of nowhere.
So we've sort of established
these upper and lower bounds.
We wanted more than 30 but less than 150.
Now that's actually a
pretty wide range of sizes,
30 to 150, that's a range of 120 pixels.
And in general, bigger
elements have more leeway
in how you size them.
So that's actually the second
heuristic for sizing elements
is that you should explore a larger range
of size options for larger elements.
Now, even though I said
okay, 30 is too small,
150 is too big, I don't
wanna go necessarily exactly
to what is halfway in between them
which is 90 in this case.
And the reason why is,
let me explain it here.
I'll just make a little
square, let's make it blue
and we'll give it a
height and width of 10.
And then I'm gonna make another
square, this is 20 by 20.
So we got 10 by 10, 20 by
20, I'm gonna do 100 by 100,
and we'll do 110 by 110.
So we've got sort of
this weird thing going on
where this square is 10 wider
and 10 taller than this one.
Likewise, this one is 10 wider
And yet the size difference,
we don't really judge to be the same.
This one feels like it's
much bigger than this one.
And sure enough, it's four times the area.
This one only feels marginally
bigger than this one.
And so there's this sense
that, at least visually,
when we're looking at
elements on our page,
not only do we need to make bigger changes
to bigger elements to feel
like the same relative
or kind of proportional change,
but also, if we've sort
of identified maybe
this is the lower bounds,
and this is the upper bounds,
numerically, what feels
like halfway in between them
is actually going to be more similar
to the smaller one than to the larger one.
So what I'm saying here is
that even though 90 as a
height is exactly in between
what we judged as being
too small and too big,
I actually probably want to make a header
that's a little bit smaller still.
If you're a developer
or technically minded,
you might understand that
kind of what I'm getting at
is you don't wanna just take the average
or the arithmetic mean between
what's too big and too small,
you're actually looking
for the geometric mean.
And so what this means practically,
even if you didn't understand
any of those words,
is whenever you've identified
what's definitely too small
and what's definitely too big,
don't just go halfway in between them.
You're gonna more often
find the best option
by going a little bit smaller than kind of
that halfway point.
And sure enough, I think 50 pixels here,
at least for a header that
just has this content in it,
actually feels really nice,
50 being much closer to
30 than it is to 150.
Now, we still have these items right here.
And honestly, I kind of
think we should include them
in a header as well.
But one way that we can do
this is make a sub navigation.
So I'm gonna duplicate our top nav,
make it a little bit bigger,
and then I'm gonna send it
to the bottom of the page.
In some sense there's 50
pixels between here and here
as well as there's 50 pixels
between here and here.
So hey, that's consistent, that's great.
But we actually have some
reason to break the consistency
because this nav is the
absolute most primary one,
it's kind of the overall
navigation on the whole page.
This one is of secondary importance.
And so I'm actually gonna
make it a little bit smaller.
Now there's only 40 pixels
for the secondary nav
but the primary nav is still 50 pixels.
So I'll grab these,
center them a little bit,
I'm actually gonna press
Shift+A to put them in a group
and then I can change the space
between the layers very
easily, that was 24.
And I might also left align them.
Now let's look at these
form controls right here.
We've got a search bar
that's gonna ultimately need
to go around this.
And let me just lock these layers
'cause we won't play with them anymore.
And then we've got a button
that's gonna go around here.
And one key thing for
sizing of form controls is
that first heuristic.
In the absence of any compelling logic
to do otherwise, go consistent.
Set in a stroke.
Of course it doesn't need
to be very thick at all.
We'll put it all the way at the bottom.
Then pull it up just enough to see it.
I'll move this here a little bit.
And then I'm just gonna
duplicate this layer.
Then I can remove the stroke.
And we'll talk about this
more in the color lesson
but I think I can just go
for kind of a nice orange
that seems to be suggested by the site.
But since this is the donate button,
I want it to be kind of bright
and attract attention a little bit.
Now I can just press Shift+A
to create an auto layout here
which will allow me to edit
the button text very nicely.
But I do want the height to
be consistent, so this is 35.
Let's just make it an even number
so it seems more intentional.
That's a huge deal either way.
We want this to be 36 as well.
So we'll switch over to a fixed height
and make it a bit bigger.
And that actually looks pretty good.
Now let's zoom out and see how this looks.
Overall, a 36 pixel form control is well
within the accepted range of what most
professionally designed
desktop web apps are doing.
I would say the minimum that
you want is a height of 30
and the maximum is probably
about a height of 50.
You'll sometimes have buttons
that are like big calls to action
at the bottom of marketing
pages that are even bigger,
maybe 55, 60, is not crazy.
Of course the text would
probably be bigger too.
But for something that's kind of limited
into this already narrow
space, 36 seems spot on.
And let's take the briefest of looks
at what some of these
other sites are doing.
One thing that's notable about the buttons
on Airtable's interface is they've got
these tag style buttons that are so small,
share and upgrade.
Most of the time I don't
recommend making buttons
that are this small because
they actually get kind of tough to click.
So that's only 22 pixels
high, not very big.
But I do appreciate
that they made the upgrade nice and orange
and the share kind of
bright and green here.
And so what they lack in the actual size,
they still make up for with bright colors
and kind of popping and catching your eye.
If we look here, we got a sign up button.
This looks like it's well within
that kind of 30 to 50 range or so,
yeah, 35 pretty normal,
but then we have these, again,
calls to action on a marketing page.
These are typically about
as big as the buttons come.
And this is only 50 pixels tall.
So pretty typical.
IDEO, no buttons throughout the blog post
but here we go, there's one.
And again, it looks
like it's gonna be right
around 50 or something, 48.
So you get the idea.
Now it's time that we
talked about font sizes.
Font sizes, if you can size them well,
I mean, this is just one of
the most important things
that you can do in
terms of a single change
that will make your design look better.
I'm gonna talk about five
different major font styles
that you'll probably use.
And honestly, most apps I think,
could get away with just having
these five styles and that's it.
If you have one size for
each of these styles,
you'll be good to go.
The first one is the body size.
And maybe I call this the
default size, the body size,
the paragraph size, the
standard size, whatever.
But the whole idea is that
most of the text on your page
that's in paragraphs or anything beyond,
just maybe a quick label or something,
anything that's in it, a text box,
some sort of description,
we're just gonna take all of these
and kind of lump them
into our default size.
Some of them we might split out later
but the idea is we want to,
again by that first heuristic
default to consistency.
Now, right now all of this
stuff is Minion Pro at 16 point.
16 point is a good starting size.
It is the default size
where if you don't add any CSS styles,
your website will just
probably start displaying
its text in 16 point.
And Minion Pro, in my opinion,
is kind of on the small side
even for any particular size.
If I were to look at some
other fonts at 16 point,
they'd actually be more
readable and maybe look bigger.
So I'm definitely gonna want
to lean a little bit big here.
How big? Well, kind of depends.
If I get as high up as 20 here,
it starts to seem like this might just be
a bit more than I want just 'cause
of how much content is on this page,
how many little different
things are going on.
20 might be a bit big, but 19...
So if 15 is too small and 20 is too big,
this is actually kind of a violation
to that third heuristic
but maybe 19, 18, somewhere
around there seems good.
Let's just do 19 for right now.
Now, I want to say one thing
about picking a body text size,
which is for pages that
have a ton going on,
I sometimes call them
highly interactive pages,
and even though this page
isn't super interactive,
you can click this link
and click this link
and there's a nav, there's
still so much going on
that it's kind of under
different constraints
than pages that are primarily text.
So for instance, if we just removed,
if we just removed everything except
for maybe one little
piece of body text here
and we said this page is all
about this text right here,
you can see that size 19
is actually probably not big enough.
We always want to have 50
to 75 characters align,
so that's two to three alphabets.
We can see that according
to this font size,
this is wide enough,
but it just doesn't take
up enough of the page.
It's so little.
And so if we wanted something
that took up a little
bit more of the page,
at this point it would be this size
and then 20 kind of
becomes the minimum size,
that makes sense and we could
actually get much bigger.
So the constraints if you have
a very text heavy site are
to try and have a larger body font size.
If you have a more interaction heavy site
where there's lots of little labels
and lots of stuff going on,
then maybe your normal default
size isn't quite as big.
If you have a site that
has both types of pages,
it can be a very careful balance.
Perhaps you'll find one size
that fits the bill for both places
and perhaps you'll just have
to have two different sizes there.
So let me straighten this out a bit
and then we'll keep going.
So now everything looks a
little bit more official
and it's a little bit neater.
Let's talk about the
top level header style,
the page title, the h1 in HTML speak.
I like to call this the h1 style
but it just means header one,
kind of the most important
header or the page title.
It's as opposed to something like h2
which could be for instance,
overview or cost effectiveness,
or even malaria consortium down here.
Now, if you remember, the second heuristic
of sizing elements in UI design is
to explore a wider range of
sizes for bigger elements.
And h1s kind of fit the bill here.
So even though I just
picked the normal size of 16
and doubled it for 32,
we can actually explore a
good deal of sizes here.
And I'm gonna press Shift+Enter
to go up to the parent
and tell him to stop clipping
content, don't need that.
Just get this stuff out of the way
until we find a good style that we like.
And I can slide up to
what's clearly too big
in the range of 50 and go down
to what's clearly too small.
And the range of 32 I feel like actually
isn't really big enough.
Now this is ultimately a decision
where this charity is just one charity
of the many charities listed on this page.
And so whatever these headlines say,
I can't just pick a size
in isolation looking at one header.
I'm gonna have to see
how this particular size,
if I pick 40, I have to see how 40 works
for all of the different
titles on the page,
or if I pick 42.
There we go.
Looks great for this.
And graphic designers can get away
with just picking one
size and having it work
for that particular piece of text
but in UI design, we know we have
to have not only this headline
but other ones on the page
and then if the page gets updated
or changed to something else,
there's always sort of this interplay
between the real data in this text box
and the font size that we choose.
If it gets to be way too long,
this just looks ridiculous.
So it's a careful balance.
Now just as text heavy sites tend
to have larger body sizes,
like the IDEO blog post,
let's see, 18 as its body size
but if we go to Airtable
which is a lot more interaction-heavy,
not there's a real body size here
but let's say it's this 14 point.
So definitely on the smaller
side and that's fine,
while as IDEO is on the bigger
side, and that works for it.
So just as that you see that
pattern for the body font size,
you'll also see it for the h1 size.
Here we have a 70 pixel header.
Again, if we flip on over to Airtable,
nothing on this page is
even close to 70 pixels.
This one's only 22,
that's ridiculously small.
That's like mildly bigger
than the body font size on this page.
Vercel looks like it's kind
of nice and in between.
Maybe we've got some big headers here,
64 point, yep, that's quite big
but then this body, what's
really the true body size?
They have a couple going on
but this one looks maybe the closest,
size 16, there you go.
Now this is actually a good
lead into talking about h2s.
So here we've got this primary
header better together.
For our secondary header
we want a font size
that is big enough to show you
that it's supposed to
be bigger than the body
but also small enough that
it doesn't get confused
with this top level header.
And for whatever reason,
when designers think about
trying to pick a size
for an h1 and an h2 and a body
text all at the same time,
they come across this
thing called type scales.
Type scales are based around this idea
that you should multiply
each successive font size
by a certain constant,
in this case, I've
picked 1.250 major third
but I can go and pick any
of these on the site here,
an act of unforgiveable pretension.
These are all named after
musical intervals except
for the golden ratio which who
even knows with this stuff?
And here, now we've got
our page title right here
and our secondary headers
and our tertiary headers on down the line.
And presumably This is
kind of the default size
that that body text is.
Now if you can't tell my
opinion at this point,
I think type scales are ridiculous.
You really should feel no compulsion
to obey one of these things exactly.
Instead, you should understand
why this is generally a good idea
but then you should adjust
type sizes as you need.
We'll cover this more
in the typography unit
but the general idea is just
having a secondary header
that kind of walks the line nicely
between your primary header
here and your body text.
It's about corralling the
users attention effectively
and giving them a sense of exactly
how important any given header is.
If we go and we look here,
we can see this is actually,
they do a fantastic job.
If I just squint my eyes here,
I can tell kind of immediately
what I'm looking at.
There's this page title which
applies to everything here,
all the stuff that I'm looking at
and then there's these
three smaller titles
which seem to be kind of in parallel
and sort of sub headers underneath this.
I don't need to be able
to perceive a single word on the page
to understand that overall
structure of the page,
and that's our goal.
One interesting thing
about type scales though,
is if you follow them exactly,
it does kind of follow our third heuristic
for sizing elements which
is that once you found
your upper bound and your lower bound,
you're always gonna choose something,
the middle so to speak
is actually always closer
to the lower bound.
If I go and I look here,
109 pixels is actually closer numerically
to 67 pixels than it is to 177 pixels.
Likewise, 16 is closer
to nine than it is to 25.
And so that general principle
can be useful to keep in mind,
but none of your users
will find your site ugly
because you didn't follow
a type scale exactly.
However, they might notice,
if your sub headers look
too much like headers
or too much like your body text.
Again, your job is just to
corral attention effectively.
All right, so our body
text size is 19 here,
so let's say that's about
20 and this is about 40.
So we could say for our sub headers,
we'd actually want to
be 30 is in the middle
and we know we'll want to be
on the the lower end of 30.
Take a bunch of these, make them 25.
Even that's a bit bigger.
If this was text-heavy page
and the individual
sections were quite long,
I actually could have
these subheaders be 25.
But in the context of this page,
these are all just gonna be
really short little snippets.
Nothing's gonna be over
a couple of lines long.
So what I'm gonna do
is actually keep them,
the size 19 for right now
and we'll come back to them
in just a bit.
But that being said,
this card that actually
gives the charity's name,
this could be 25 and
that seems to work fine.
So now we've talked about
three different font sizes.
We've talked about the body text size,
which we use, not just for paragraph text,
but also for labels or for
text that's inside inputs
or maybe kind of like
little descriptive labels.
It can be anywhere.
And in general, while
we might change the size
of some of those, it's
just our default go to size
whenever we're putting
something new on the screen.
We talked about the h1
and we said we'll explore
a much wider range of values for this.
Ultimately, we settled on 42 here.
And then we talked about the h2.
There's only one little
occurrence of it on this page,
Malaria Consortium 25.
It's closer to the body text
size than it is to the h1.
If you have a very very
structured document in particular,
you might need to make h3s and h4s,
then you kind of have to just
play with the font sizes again
so that people can immediately
look at the subtitle
and know just how important
or what level it's at.
But we're not really going
to bother with that here
because the vast majority of
sites don't actually need h4s
and h5s and h6s.
Instead, I'm gonna move on
to an extremely common
font size in UI design
which is the secondary font size.
And you've probably seen
me do this a little bit
but it's one of the most rote
and predictable font sizes in UI design.
It's very, very standard and
I mean this in a good way.
I mean, you just know
what you should be doing
'cause everyone should basically be doing
the same thing here.
To take some piece of secondary text,
maybe it's a label that's
just not quite as important
and make it two font sizes smaller.
I suppose you could theoretically do one
or maybe you could do
three, occasionally two,
but two just seems to work really well.
Take my body text size and
make it a little bit smaller
and then the other thing I'm gonna do
is make it a little bit lighter.
Just press eight and get 80% opacity here.
Now this feels quite secondary,
even compared to this text right here.
I'm actually gonna do the same thing
with these little links,
how good is these links?
I'm not gonna change the
color 'cause it's already blue
and I don't wanna make it too light
but I can bring it down to size 17.
And it feels a little bit secondary.
The secondary font size works
for details or annotations
or sometimes captions.
It's like anything that feels like
you're piping in with from the side,
what's the cost effectiveness?
you could save a life for two to $3,000.
How good is this, like,
hey, you wanna know how good this is?
It's sort of a comment from the side.
And that's really what the
secondary text size is all about.
And the final size or
styling I wanna talk about
in our big five is labels.
Labels are maybe slightly less common
if you're just making a
primarily text based site,
though it's not to say
you'll never see them.
Labels are much more common
when you have say little
small pieces of UI.
A label could be in a menu,
a label could be for content.
A lot of times a label
is actually referring
to a specific text input
or selection control.
Labels are interesting
because, in my opinion,
one extremely reliable go to trick
with labels is to make them uppercase.
So it's gonna be hard to select all these.
Let me goo to my Similayer plugin
and select everything
with the same size, style.
There we go.
Yeah, that just got all of them.
Now I'm gonna use my keyboard shortcut,
Command+Shift+U, make these uppercase.
And as soon as I make them uppercase,
you can see almost immediately
that they appear too big and too bold.
So there's a couple ways we combat that.
One is by making them smaller.
So this is why they're
often their own size
to 18, 17.
Another is by making them lighter,
could set them at say 70%
opacity or 80% opacity,
maybe 80 feels about Right
but then I also have this issue
that making Serif fonts in particular,
uppercase just feels a little bit goofy.
It can work especially when I
letter space them generously
but right now it doesn't really feel
like the right place for that.
And so fortunately, we use
another font right here,
DIN 2014, since we're
already loading it up,
try switching that over.
Maybe I don't want bold
but I want demi bold,
demi bold, however you say it.
Play with letter spacing a little bit,
the opacity, size some more.
Yeah, and there we go, landed at 16
and that really does not feel so bad.
I like that quite a bit.
I'm also gonna take this label style
and just try applying it
here and see how it goes.
You can make them by default lighter,
but the page that we're
on, "Top Charities",
make that maybe a little bit darker
and we can just give it a nice
little selected state here.
I'll use the same blue highlight color
that I had below.
There we go, looking good.
Now we just have this image
which feels about the right size
'cause it kind of competes
nicely with the text
and feels relatively as important
and sort of doesn't feel too
big, doesn't feel too small.
So the very last thing that I'm gonna do
is just add a little decorative element.
All these little labels
and all these references
to research and stuff,
just make this site feel
like a little bit more
of a techie brand.
And so what I'm gonna
do is just add something
that kind of adds to that
techie feel to the site.
And we'll bring the picture
of this boy to the front,
move him down so that he's flush here,
kind of have him overlap
this wraparound shape
in the background.
And I will just put on one more
little highlight behind him,
just something subtle in a color
that's based on his clothing here
and then I wanna mask it.
So go with an intersection,
move layer to the back and there we go.
I think this looks good
and now let's tackle the mobile version.
So I'm gonna press A to bring
up my different frame sizes.
I'll just pick this iPhone 11.
375 is a good phone size,
at least because it's right in
the middle for iPhone widths.
Technically, if I knew a lot of my users
were gonna be on 320, it might
be better to start there.
But 375 is at least smaller than 414.
And in general, when
I'm designing on mobile,
I wanna start with a narrow screen size
'cause it's the tighter constraint.
If something works at 375,
it's almost certainly gonna work
if I make the screen 50 pixels bigger.
So we'll rename this charity mobile.
Let's start bringing on
over the same elements
that we have here.
And actually the very first thing
that I'm gonna do is put
in some rulers on the side.
So Shift+R to bring up rulers in Figma,
slide them in from the side.
I'm gonna put one at 16,
which is the side margin
that's most common for
both iOS and Android,
and 359, which is 375 minus 16.
And I'll just put it in
one in the middle too
which I think is 188.
Yeah, 187.5.
So 188 just works perfectly.
And then I'm gonna take
this hamburger button
and align it with the 16
point ruler right here.
And on mobile, just 'cause
the screen's not as wide,
you don't have that many places
that you can align things.
So use them when you can.
Having a little side margin
right here is a huge way
to buy yourself more alignment
with the same elements.
I'll throw on a Donate button right here
but already I know one of the
biggest changes I need to make
is it needs to be 44 pixels tall.
And this is because
of the iPhone tap target size guidelines.
Anything that I need to
tap, anything at all,
buttons, text, input,
controls, switches, whatever,
on iPhone, it should own a space
of 44 pixels by 44
pixels absolute minimum.
And so actually, you sometimes end up
with an interesting situation
where your buttons on mobile are bigger
than your buttons on desktop.
And that's totally fine.
I'm here to give you
permission to do that.
We ultimately just wanna make
things easy for our users.
Yeah, and this button was so chunky
that I figured rather than kind of have it
maybe look a little awkward there,
I will just bring it off to the side
and it'll have a consistent
four pixels of space
or three pixels of spacing all the way
around it in this header.
Of course, this is technically
only 20 pixels wide
but if it owns this whole tap target,
then it has 48 pixels of space.
And by the way, I said 44 is
the tap target size for iPhone,
48 is the tab target size for Android.
So if you're designing
something for Android,
which of course this is a mobile website,
people could be using it for Android too.
It's always better to lean
just a little bit bigger.
So there we go, if this is 19 pixels wide,
it's 244 minus 19, 15.
So we need at least seven
pixels of space on each side
but I think that will be plenty
to have a nice generous tap target size.
Now, the way I sort of
perceive this site working,
all of these things would be
in the hamburger menu here
and if I tap this, then
I'd get some slide out
or fly down or however
it wants to animate in
but I would see my menu that way.
So we can just move on
to the actual page content right here.
Grab this, I'll paste it in.
What we need to do is make
this go from left to right.
So let's talk about how to
adjust these font sizes.
The h1 clearly needs to
be adjusted the most here.
If you look at a variety of
well designed mobile websites,
you'll see h1s are typically
in the 25 to 45 range.
But oftentimes, it'll only be
on that larger side of things
if they're very short titles.
So you can see 25 here
does feel a bit small.
If I go and I view this on my device,
I'll find something like 34 makes sense.
And by the way, I highly recommend
for mobile viewing and on device.
I'm doing that and then
another way to do it
is even if I don't have my phone handy,
I can go into presentation mode.
I find at least that this
size is actually much closer
to my actual iPhone size
than when I'm designing it
in the designer part of the app.
I believe Figma is
intentionally shrinking down
the pixels of my computer so
that I'm essentially seeing
my design at the size it
would appear on my phone.
And one other little thing about sizing,
we'll talk more about this,
but line spacing does
not need to be as high
when you have very short lines.
The whole point of line
spacing is to help your eye get
from one line to the next and
when the lines are so short,
it just doesn't need much help.
So we can make that a little bit smaller.
As far as the labels, these
work totally fine at 16 point.
The body text here is 19
point which also works good.
The only real thing to keep
in mind for body text size
is never go below 16 on
mobile or else iPhone,
at least when you click on a form input,
will do this weird zooming
thing and kind of mess
with how you're viewing
the mobile website.
So just make sure your base text size,
your normal text size on
mobile is at least 16.
19 is also gonna work here.
For a little bit of context,
iPhone uses SF Pro text
in 17 point as their default font size
and Android uses Roboto
in 16 point as their default font size.
So you get a sense of how
big these are in comparison.
Overall, this 19 point minion
seems to work pretty well.
Now I'm gonna bring my card over.
And one thing I'm gonna do,
if you remember from the alignment lesson
is I'm gonna have the
card go a little bit past
this normal line of
alignment so that the content
in the card, which has maybe
a little bit more contrast
with its background, can all be aligned
with the other content on the page.
And then on mobile, unfortunately,
you're only gonna get a
smaller version of this logo,
because that's all we have room for.
This blue bar still feels a bit close.
There we go, and this is
looking quite a bit better.
So the final thing I wanna do
is transfer this image on over.
And we talk about this a lot more
in the responsive design video.
But essentially, when
you're sizing an image
on a mobile design, you may
not do it in quite the same way
that you would on desktop.
For instance, not only do I
wanna make this guy smaller
but even when he's smaller,
because he's so tall,
so much taller than he is wide,
I have this awkward space around here.
And so this specific image might
just be tough to work with.
So one industry term, it's
a bit of a weird term,
but we call it art
direction, which is to say,
you just kind of do things
besides just resizing an
image when you move to mobile
such that the feel of the image
or the feel of the artwork
or whatever stays the same
but it's just in a little bit
different of a form factor.
It's something that
works better for mobile.
So I'll do that there.
And honestly, I don't really want
to have this big gray line
going all over the place
on mobile because I think
it would just take away.
There's just so little space as it is.
But maybe I just keep that gray line
in the context of having
one little line right there.
And it's going from one
ruler to the other ruler.
So we'll put that there
and I'll take this little circle highlight
and we'll put that behind them.
But again, in the
interest of art direction,
it's gonna need to be a
slightly different shape.
And I realized this is
a little bit messed up.
Did I even notice that this didn't work?
So there we go.
As far as the sizing goes,
I've got a good body text size.
If I viewed it on my device,
I know I can read it,
the labels make sense, the
secondary text can stay the same,
the h2, that also stayed the same,
although it's not inconceivable
that it would need to
get a little bit smaller.
And the biggest change was having
this h1 come down quite a bit.
And this video is going
long enough anyways
but if you heed my advice at the start,
which is to always go and look
at what good sites are doing,
you'll see that this is very much the case
where large text sizes on desktop,
whether they're 40, or 50, or 60, or 70,
often come on down into
this range of about 30.
And that wraps it up for sizing
your elements in UI design.
So just as you go and
size different elements
in your own designs,
remember the three heuristics
that we talked about today.
First of all, to default to consistency,
to make everything as
consistent as possible,
unless there's an overwhelming
reason not to do so.
And I'll just mention now,
'cause I forgot to earlier,
the worst offender here
is default font sizes.
Make sure to keep those consistent.
The second heuristic we talked
about was just a helpful tip,
which is to explore a
wider range of values
when you're working with larger elements.
That's just sort of the way sizing works.
And along those same lines,
the third heuristic that we talked about,
was whenever you've
identified a lower bound
and an upper bound, usually
the optimum sizing wise
is kind of in that lower half of values,
just based on how geometric means work.
So take those three tips
and just sort of keep them in mind
as you're working on your design.
And again, I'll just repeat one more time,
if you only take one thing
away from this lesson,
let it be anytime you wanna
make some 80 pixel button
or 120 pixel header, just go and look
at what other sites are doing first,
just the very best sites,
the most professionally designed sites
that you'd like to imitate,
and see if you can figure out the logic
behind why they're doing
what they're doing.
Because in the end,
we're largely not trying
to reinvent the wheel here.
There's certain sizes that make
sense for certain elements.
Let me know if you have any questions
in the student community.
Take a look at the resources
in the homework below
and we will see you in the next lesson.